[Music]
You'll see many cases on social media
where health insurance is
declared a scam, saying
someone paid premiums consistently for years, like
a loyal client, for 10 years, for 15 years,
and when they actually fell ill, were
hospitalized, and made a claim, they were
n't paid. We lose all faith in
health insurance. We feel like the
entire industry is a scam. Maybe
that's why 82% of Indian households do
n't have health insurance, even
when medical inflation
is double the normal inflation. This means treatment is becoming more expensive at a rate of 14% every year.
If medical
inflation is so high, then if there's a truly
reliable health insurance plan that,
when we really
need it, does
n't deny us the claim by citing clauses, exceptions, or excuses, and
comes to our rescue in times of need. If there's truly such a reliable,
trusted health insurance plan, then the premium for 51 Haj is
10 lakh.  Who would
not want to pay for insurance? I am sure every Indian is
intelligent enough. The problem
is trust. The right choice. There are a
lot of options and content in the market, but we don't understand
whom to trust. We don't understand
who is talking after taking money, who is
selling a policy for his own benefit, so there is a
trust deficit. This is what we are
addressing in this video today so that every Indian,
when faced with a medical emergency, has
a reliable health insurance that
helps him and he does
n't have to withdraw money from his SIP or mutual fund by selling a plot.
His financial goals are not derailed.
If someone goes to the hospital due to hospitalization, there is a sure loss of Rs 57 lakh, so
our goals get derailed.
That should not happen. I will
pick you step by step in this video a reliable health insurance
that will not be of any use in times of need and will
not make excuses. This is Pranjal Kamra
with Finology. Today we help you in choosing
a perfect health insurance plan for yourself.
Now before that, there is one
important question many people ask.  They do not take health insurance
because they say that we have a
corporate health insurance policy, it is
covered in it, see if it is there then it is a good thing, it is not bad,
but it has its limitations, the
good thing is that it will also be useful but
it will not provide complete coverage because
many times partial
claim exemption is limited in it, you do
not get the amount you need,
thirdly, if you are switching jobs
then there is a gap in between, it is possible that you may
not get it in the new company, we forget to
take health insurance at that time, so there is a
problem of reliability,
fourthly, when the company is giving this benefit, then many
companies try to save cost in it, hence you do
not get a comprehensive policy, you do
not get comprehensive coverage, there are a lot of
exceptions and exclusions in it
and we live under this false illusion
that we have a
corporate health insurance plan, it is a
good thing, but do not trust it completely, in
most cases most people should also take their own individual plan,
if it is there in your company then at least find out about those
around them  If
your colleague has filed a claim, their claim experience will give
you a sense of
reliability. The second
question arises: if I already have a
major illness, such as hypertension, diabetes,
or have undergone a minor surgery, then we assume that I won't
get it at all. No, I'll get it
in that case too. Yes, it will be expensive. The
premium will be higher than for a completely healthy person. But
you will still get health insurance. So, do
n't lose hope, thinking that I wo
n't get it at all or it will be very expensive. At least get the best
quotation, perhaps you can afford it.
But keep in mind:
don't hide your illness in order to save premium. If you
hide your illness, then understand that your
premium is going to go down the drain every year. You wo
n't get a claim every year. You will be able to claim your claim
from the insurance company only if
you have honestly disclosed every illness.
Even if the premium increases,
you should be sure that they won't know anything.
Trust me, they are in this business;
they deal with thousands of customers like you.
They are going to know everything.  Do
not hide anything from them, rather the
premium you are paying will be lost, the health
insurance company will find an excuse,
please do not hide it, thirdly, what is the minimum
coverage we need so that we feel a little comfortable
and safe, look individuals, if you are
in your 20s-30s and living in big cities, then
you should go for a coverage of 10 lakhs, if you have a
family of three-four people, again
living in cities, in big cities there should be a family plan of 10 to 15
lakhs, it
needs to be increased in multiples because it is
very unlikely that more than one
person gets hospitalized, hence
10 lakhs for an individual and if there is a family of three-
four then 10, if not 15 lakhs, there is
no need to increase it too much, yes if you are
in your 50s, have a pre-aging disease and you can afford it, then
I would say you should
go for a coverage of up to 20 lakhs, now the next
question is from where should you buy insurance,
go directly to the website of the insurance company
and take help from their agent,
see, in that case it  It's possible that a
company will only promote its health insurance plan, and
you won't get a fair consultation or a
fair choice. This is where an
insurance advisory aggregator like Ditto can be
useful. They provide unbiased advice,
understand your situation, and choose the
best plan for you. They
can provide personalized choices. So,
if you need personalized recommendations, I think
Ditto is a good choice. But
what I've done in this video
is apply a general filter based on well-
established industry-standard
parameters. I'll walk you through them step by step,
and generally, I'll give you some of the best choices based on which health
insurance policies perform best in these general parameters.
But
this is general, I do
n't know your particular situation. Which city you're in,
which company type is better there, and all
these variations with hospitals, an
advisor like Ditto will be able to tell you better. So, you can
also review my processes and then consult them if you
need more.
You will get the link in the description. Now
look, first of all, there is this table on your screen.
We rejected all those policies
which did not have these options. For example,
we do not like those policies which have disease
wise limits, that your plan is of 10
lakhs, but if you get this disease, you will
pay only 2 lakhs, if you get that disease, you will pay 3 lakhs.
Any such plan has been removed from this list. If you are imposing a
limit on room rent, that private
room is allowed, but
₹2000000 is required.
You should get at least one health checkup once a year. The health insurance
company should provide free ambulance. If you are falling ill, you will go
by ambulance only.
In case of emergency, the health insurance should also pay the ambulance expenses.
We have not included the policies which do not provide this.
Apart from this, what is pre and post
hospitalization? Many companies
pay the expenses till hospitalization,
but before that, if there are any diagnostic
checks, after that there is post operative care, you have left the
hospital, but if there are regular
checkups and medicines, then you should get that too, at least.
30 days before and 60 days
after. After this, day care if
hospitalization is not required on that day but is
kept for a day from morning till evening, that should also be
covered. The age limit should not be flexible,
so we have taken such policies which
cover up to 75 years. After this,
in case of organ donation, the expenses of the person donating the organ will
also be covered, that should also be covered.
If there is hospitalization at home, the
hospital setup has come to the home, is that
covered? That should also be
considered as hospitalization, that is also important.
Look at the waiting period for pre-assisting diseases, it should be
maximum 3 years. If it is
less than this, then we have given brownie points to it.
We have checked all these things and have
rejected such plans and companies
which do not have this so that the
chances of getting a wrong policy are minimized. Now
apart from this, we have some company-wise data and
company-wise steps. We have
also applied those filters. I will take you there now. There are
18 health insurance companies in the country,
we have eliminated them with this filter.
So, using this table (the previous table),
we eliminated individual policies. And
now, using the filter, we eliminated health
insurance manufacturers or companies.
First, we looked at the claim
settlement ratio. We needed it to be above 90 percent,
meaning that if 100 claims are filed
against a company, at least 90 percent of them should be
paid. When we applied this filter,
five out of 18 companies were eliminated because
their ratio was less than 90 percent.
Next, we looked at the solvency ratio. We
needed it to be at least 1.5 percent,
so that the company does not have to
spend financially on claims. Now, if this
ratio is above ₹1, meaning more than ₹1,000,000 had to be paid, it
means the company's
underwriting is not good. It is
taking excessive risks and, for growth, it
is offering policies to high-risk candidates,
which will worsen the company's financial condition.
Now, don't look at this one-year ratio.  There
may be more claims in some year but
we have seen them for 3 years, so we have
taken the average of 3 years. Conversely, if this ratio is very
low, say below 60, that is, it is
going less than ₹1000000, then here
we are seeing that the company is stingy,
perhaps it hesitates to pay the premium even in rare cases, so there should be
a balance in it.
We saw that if it is between 60 to 85, then
it is good. So when we
applied this filter, two more companies out of six were
eliminated, four companies remained. After this, there were
no specific criteria on the
basis of which elimination should not be done, but
we considered these plans, on the basis of which
we did not do strict elimination,
but we considered these factors to
choose our top two winners,
but these four plans are good because
they also have weightage on your area geographical location,
like how good is their tie-up with the hospital,
network of
hospitals where they are cashless.  Payments are made,
then what is the policy contract like? Are there
many conditions or few? Then,
affordability? Similar person quotations vary in different
places. Who is more affordable?
Who offers product variety and customization?
Now, these are all minor factors.
I don't want to eliminate anyone based on these.
But when we did raffle testing,
in most cases, we felt that the
health plans of two companies would suit most people. The
first is Ekko's Platinum
Health Insurance Plan and the second is
Aditya Birla's Active One Max Plan.
Ekko's consumer complaint number
is 17 per 100,000 clients, while the
industry average is 22. So, this makes sense.
You can rely on Aditya
Birla's 22, which is the industry average.
So, we did not want companies whose
number is higher than the industry average. In
a way, this shows that they are
fulfilling their promises.
Just make the policy affordable and attractive with
all the features.  Even after giving good advice, the
focus is not on selling, so consumer
feedback gives us double insurance
through this data that what we have paid is actually right,
but as I
told you, I am talking in general here,
I am asking specific questions like your location, if you have any pre-
existing disease in your family, if
you want to take a floater plan, then what
is their age profile, I
cannot customize the plan according to various use cases
because I do not know your
requirements, here
Ditto Insurance can give you unbiased advice, so if
you really want to take health insurance right now,
which you have not taken, then please
take it, you can contact the insurance,
another good thing is that you will
not get any spam calls here, the advice is
unbiased and spam free,
you will not get calls from all over the world and apart from this,
God forbid you have to take a claim
because you have taken this insurance through them, then they will
help you in the claim also, so it will become
like a single point of contact for you and this  Doing all this will
not increase your insurance premium. Whether
you buy directly from the insurance company or
from Ditto, the premium you pay is
not going to be affected, so the cost is
not going to increase. In fact, you can download and read all the
terms and conditions of any policy
from Ditto's website. If you have any
doubts about
why this policy is like this or that,
Ditto will clarify those doubts for you
absolutely free of cost. So, whenever
you are confused about any policy,
you can take Ditto's help. There is a link
in the video description in the card above. Keep in
mind that whatever
filters I have told you, they are also
unbiased. No one can sponsor our
result as to which policy we
like. Our choice of policies is not sponsored, it will never be sponsored.
But on top of that, the additional services that
Ditto is providing you, I personally think it's worth it
and you should try that out.
Similarly, transparently and honestly, we will
keep making videos and I hope  I hope
this video has solved your health
insurance problem.
Please share this video with your friends
and family and help them decide on
health insurance and choose the plan that
actually helps them when the need arises. This is
Pranjal Kamra signing off bye-bye.